Finding Aid for Wilfred Kaplan papers, 1936-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilfred Kaplan papers 1936-2002
Kaplan, Wilfred
5.5 linear feet
03122 Aa 2
Professor of mathematics at the University of Michigan, officer and long-time member of the American Association of University Professors, especially its University of Michigan chapter. Papers relate to his career as a mathematics professor at the University of Michigan, his active involvement with the University of Michigan Chapter of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), as well as a series regarding his involvement with the Ann Arbor Unitarian Fellowship. Materials also include the personal correspondence of the Kaplan family.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Wilfred Kaplan (Donor No. 8901 ) and came to the library in 2001. An addition was made in July 2008 after his death.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Wilfred Kaplan, professor of mathematics at the University of Michigan from 1940 to 1986, was born November 28, 1915 in Boston Massachusetts to Jacob and Anne Kaplan. He attended Harvard University, where he completed his A.B. Degree in 1936 and his Ph.D. degree in mathematics in 1939. Kaplan earned a Rogers Traveling Fellowship from Harvard University to study Mathematics in Europe during the 1936-1937 school terms. At ETH Zurich, in Zurich, Switzerland, he met Ida Roettinger in a mathematics course. He lovingly nicknamed her Heidi. The two were married in 1938. Professor Kaplan was an instructor at the College of William and Mary from 1939 to 1940, and came to the University of Michigan in 1940. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1944, to associate professor in 1950, and to full professor in 1956.
Professor Kaplan's early research was concerned with the topological behavior of the solutions of differential equations. His research interests turned to complex function theory and in 1955, he introduced and studied a class of schlicht functions, and showed that the Bieberbach conjecture held for that class of functions. At the time it was a major result and the full Bieberbach conjecture was not proven until thirty years later. His later research centered in applied mathematics and global analysis of analytical differential equations.
He was named collegiate professor for the period of 1973-1975 in recognition of his accomplishments as a teacher. Professor Kaplan's writings show the same clarity and directness that characterized his lectures. It was inevitable that he would turn his hand to writing texts in various areas of applied mathematics and intermediate analysis. The result was a series of very important and influential books. The titles of some of Kaplan's works are: Advanced Calculus; Maxima and Minima with Applications: Practical Optimization and Duality; Operational Methods for Systems; Calculus and Linear Algebra; and Advanced Mathematics for Engineers.
For over thirty years Professor Kaplan was continually active in the affairs of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP). The AAUP is a national organization founded in 1915, dedicated to defending faculty rights, especially academic freedom and tenure. The University of Michigan Chapter was founded in the mid-1920s to protect professors from arbitrary dismissal and harassment; it assures due process when a professor is charged.
During Kaplan's involvement with the University of Michigan Chapter of the AAUP, he helped establish the Academic Freedom Lecture Fund. The purpose of the AFLF is to protect academic and intellectual freedoms and to be reminded of their value and vulnerability.
Wilfred Kaplan retired from active faculty status as of May 31, 1986, and was honored by the Regents as Professor Emeritus of Mathematics. In retirement Professor Kaplan was still active within the university community and served on the executive committee of the AAUP, on the AFLF board of directors, and as president of the University of Michigan Retirees Association. For many years, Kaplan was involved with the Ann Arbor Unitarian Fellowship serving in many offices including secretary/treasurer.
Upon the death of his wife Ida "Heidi" Kaplan in 2005, Kaplan began the task of preserving and translating the correspondence between the couple from their first meeting in 1936 to their marriage in 1938. Initially, it was out of grief and for the benefit of family and friends that he organized the letters but the process evolved. The result was a two-volume book entitled Heidi and Bill: Beginning of our Life Together. A copy is currently held by the University of Michigan Shapiro Science Undergraduate Library under the call number: QA 29 .K315 A35 2005. With the book completed, Kaplan continued to organize, and in many cases translate, his entire collection of family correspondence, including those between Heidi and her family in Switzerland.
Wilfred Kaplan passed away December 26, 2007 following a short illness.
The papers of Wilfred Kaplan consist of five and a half linear feet of materials. Those relating to his career at the University of Michigan Department of Mathematics date from 1958 to 1986. The materials involving the University of Michigan Chapter of the American Association of University Professors date from 1972 to 2000. The most heavily documented of these are from the years 1980 to 1995. The personal correspondence of the Kaplan family covers the years 1936-1956, 1958, 1962-1970, 1980-1981, and 1985. The papers are divided into three series with fifteen sub-series.
Subjects:
Kaplan, Wilfred, 1915-; Kaplan, Ida Roettinger, 1913-; American Association of University Professors. University of Michigan Chapter.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- University of Michigan Dept. of Mathematics and Related Material
  The University of Michigan Department of Mathematics and Related Material series includes three sub-series. Administrative files, which includes memos circulated throughout the department and newsletters detailing the accomplishments of students and faculty of the University of Michigan Mathematics Department. The course notes sub-series is the largest section relating to Kaplan's mathematics career. The sub-series contains lecture notes, class assignments, exams, and solutions for homework assignments. Most of the materials are from the course Mathematics 571 from the years 1980-1986.
  - Administrative Files
    - Mathematics Department Administration (Box 1)
    - Notes on Divisors on Riemann Surfaces (Box 1)
    - Mathematics at the University of Michigan (Box 1)
    - Publications by Wilfred Kaplan 1991-2000 (Box 1)
    - MATLAB Remarks (Box 1)
  - Course Notes
    - Mathematics 308 (Box 1)
    - Mathematics 571 1980-1982, 1986, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Mathematics 601, Fall 1966 (Box 1)
- American Association of University Professors (University of Michigan Chapter)
  The American Association of University Professors (University of Michigan Chapter) series contains five sub-series. The Organizational materials sub-series includes financial records, general meeting advertisements, newsletters, and memos. It is arranged alphabetically by topic .The Correspondence sub-series documents the years 1972 to 2000. The sub-series contains correspondence of Kaplan, members of the AAUP National organization, University of Michigan Chapter members, University officials, and others. It is arranged chronologically. The Minutes sub-series is arranged chronologically and contains the minutes of the chapter and the executive committee meetings. The Reports sub-series documents research done by AAUP chapter members into various university related issues. It is arranged chronologically. The Topical Series is the largest series in the collection and is arranged alphabetically by topic and relates to the various issues the AAUP dealt with during Kaplan's involvement.
  - Organizational Materials
    - AAUP Policy Document and Reports 1973 (Box 1)
    - General Meeting Advertisements 1972-1997 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1983-2000 (Box 1)
    - Membership Advertisements (Box 1)
    - AAUP Memos 1972-1994 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - AAUP Memos 1995-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Newsletters-UM Chapter 1974-2001 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Newsletters-Michigan Conference 1979-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1983-2000 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence 1972-1988 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1989-2000, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Minutes
    - Chapter Meeting Minutes 1991-1999 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1972-1984 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1985-2000, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Reports 1978-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Meeting Reports 1992, 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - Wilfred Kaplan's Meeting Statements 1983-2000 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Topical
    - Academic Freedom Lecture Fund (AFLF)
      - AFLF Correspondence 1989-1998 (Box 2)
      - AFLF Income Tax Exempt Status 1991 (Box 2)
      - AFLF Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - AFLF Organizational Materials (Box 2)
      - AFLF Possible Speakers (Box 2)
      - AFLF Programs and Postings (Box 2)
      - AFLF Resolutions and Meeting Minutes 1989-1999 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Annuitants Association (Box 2)
    - 76th Annual Meeting June 16, 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Department of Humanities in the College of Engineering 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Elimination of Geography Department 1981, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Faculty Involvement and Governance 1992, 1994, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Salaries and Collective Bargaining 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Grievance Policy Administration 1973-1999 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Grievance Policy Correspondence 1972-1999 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Governance Conference September 6-8, 1996 Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Harassment Policies at the University of Michigan 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Library Staff Salaries Increase 1982 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Article Clippings (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Article Clippings on Davis, Markert, and Nickerson 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - Retirement 1973-1988 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Restitution for Davis, Markert, and Nickerson 1989 (Box 3)
    - Search for New President of the University of Michigan 1996 (Box 3)
    - Tenure Discussions 1974-1997 (Box 3)
- Ann Arbor Unitarian Fellowship 1971-2002
  The Ann Arbor Unitarian Fellowship series, 1972 to 2002, is arranged alphabetically and contains correspondence and sermon-presentation notes accrued by Wilfred Kaplan during his membership with the fellowship and from his term as their treasurer. A few of the sermons were written and presented by Kaplan himself. Also included, are the programming schedules, minutes, agendas, and papers from the Ann Arbor Unitarian Fellowship.
  - Agendas and Minutes 1977-2002 (Box 3)
  - General Information undated (Box 3)
  - Kaplan Papers 1971-2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Program Schedules 1982-2002 (Box 3)
- Personal Correspondence
  The Personal Correspondence series contains personal letters, postcards, and telegrams of the Kaplan family covering the years 1936 to 1956, 1958, 1962 to 1970, 1980 to 1981, and 1985. The series is arranged chronologically under different sub-series. Given the time-span of the correspondence, many interesting insights into history are observable. Topics lightly discussed amongst family members include World War II, McCarthyism, President Kennedy's assassination, and the Vietnam War. The correspondence begins in 1936 during Kaplan's study abroad trip. The majority of the early letters and a significant amount of the later letters are in German. The sub-series "Bill to Heidi" encompasses the years 1936 to 1938, shortly after the pair met in Zurich, Switzerland. These letters are those that Bill wrote to Heidi as he continued his study abroad program in Europe. The sub-series "Heidi to Bill" are from the years 1936 to 1938 and are those letters Heidi wrote to Bill during his time abroad and his return to the United States. The Family Correspondence sub-series covers the years 1938 to 1956, 1962 to 1970, 1980 to 1981, and 1985. These letters, which commence following the marriage of Bill and Heidi in 1938, include those between the couple as well as those from or to them from their parents, siblings, and friends. The transcribed letters series features computer print-outs of the letters Kaplan worked to preserve and translate covering the years 1936 to 1957. The essays series features essays in German that Heidi and Bill wrote to each other during their courtship discussing topics such as; marriage, mathematics, and music. The personal diaries series includes Heidi's diary from a trip to Berkeley in 1960 and her diaries from the years 1970 and 1971.
  - "Bill to Heidi"
    - December 26, 1936-July 18, 1937 (Box 4)
    - July 19, 1937-December 30, 1937 (Box 4)
    - January 7, 1938-March 31, 1938 (Box 4)
    - April 1, 1938-June 24, 1938 (Box 4)
  - "Heidi to Bill"
    - December 31, 1936-July 23, 1937 (Box 4)
    - July 24, 1937-January 4, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Family Correspondence
    - July 1938-December 1938 (Box 4)
    - August 1938-December 1938 (Box 4)
    - January 1939-June 1939 (Box 4)
    - June 1939-December 1939 (Box 4)
    - January 1940-December 1940 (Box 4)
    - January 1941-December 1941 (Box 4)
    - January 1942-June 1942 (Box 4)
    - July 1942-December 1942 (Box 4)
    - January 6, 1943-December 31, 1943 (Box 4)
    - January 1944-March 1944 (Box 4)
    - January 1944-July 1944 (Box 4)
    - July 1944-December 1944 (Box 4)
    - January 1945-June 1945 (Box 4)
    - Personal Correspondence (Box 4)
    - July 1945-December 1945 (Box 4)
    - January 1946-June 1946 (Box 4)
    - July 1946-December 1946 (Box 4)
    - January 1947-June 1947 (Box 5)
    - July 1947-December 1947 (Box 5)
    - January 1948-July 1948 (Box 5)
    - August 1948-December 1948 (Box 5)
    - January 1949-August 1949 (Box 5)
    - September 1949-December 1949 (Box 5)
    - January 1950-August 1950 (Box 5)
    - September 1950-December 1950 (Box 5)
    - January 1951-July 1951 (Box 5)
    - August 1951-December 1951 (Box 5)
    - January 1952-April 1952 (Box 5)
    - April 1952-December 1952 (Box 5)
    - January 1953-December 1953 (Box 5)
    - January 1954-December 1954 (Box 5)
    - January 1955-December 1955 (Box 5)
    - January 1956-December 1956 (Box 5)
    - 1958-Correspondence with Earl Crisler (Box 5)
    - January 1962-December 1962 (Box 5)
    - January 1963-June 1963 (Box 5)
    - July 1963-December 1963 (Box 5)
    - January 1964-June 1964 (Box 5)
    - July 1964-December 1964 (Box 5)
    - January 1965-June 1965 (Box 5)
    - July 1965-December 1965 (Box 6)
    - January 1966-December 1966 (Box 6)
    - January 1967-December 1967 (Box 6)
    - January 1968-June 1968 (Box 6)
    - July 1968-December 1968 (Box 6)
    - January 1969-June 1969 (Box 6)
    - July 1969-December 1969 (Box 6)
    - January 1970-June 1970 (Box 6)
    - July 1970-December 1970 (Box 6)
    - 1980-1981 1985 (Box 6)
  - Transcribed Letters
    - August 1936-May 1937 (Box 6)
    - January 1938-December 1938 (Box 6)
    - August 1944-December 1945 (Box 6)
    - December 1945-December 1947 (Box 6)
    - January 1948-December 1949 (Box 6)
    - January 1950-December 1952 (Box 6)
    - December 1952-February 1957 (Box 6)
  - Essays
    - By Ida "Heidi" Kaplan Undated (Box 6)
    - By Wilfred Kaplan Undated (Box 6)
  - Personal Diaries
    - Ida "Heidi" Kaplan 1960 (Box 6)
    - Ida "Heidi" Kaplan 1970-1971 (Box 6)